{"tossups": [{"question": "The Delimitation Protocol between these two countries failed to resolve the undefined area of Bozai Gumbaz. A quasi-war between these two countries began when William Bentinck attempted to establish a trade route to Bukhara and culminated in a military standoff in the Panjdeh Incident. The Pamir Boundary Commission helped mediate one rivalry between these two empires by setting the border of Afghanistan, thus ending the \u201cGreat Game.\u201d For ten points, name these two colonizing empires that were led by Queen Victoria and Tsar Nicholas I respectively.", "answer": "<b> Russia and</b> the<b> U</b>nited<b> K</b>ingdom (accept Great<b> Britain</b> or<b> England</b> for UK; do not accept the Soviet Union for Russia)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This group was satirized in a Puck cartoon that depicted its members as planets revolving around Richard Croker. William Mooney was elected as the first Grand Sachem of this group, whose name derives from a leader of the Lenape Tribe. After the most famous leader of this group died in Ludlow Street Jail, it was purged by \u201cHonest\u201d John Kelly. The Locofoco faction was formed to oppose this group, which was depicted as a tiger killing democracy in a Thomas Nast cartoon. For ten points, name this New York political machine controlled by Boss Tweed.", "answer": "<b> Tammany Hall</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Anthony van Dyck created a portrait of Charles I in the midst performing this action, dismounted from his horse. In another painting illustrating labors of different months, people who attempted this action return unsuccessfully down a snowy hillside. A series of seven works depicting this action culminates includes one of the title animal \u201cat the fountain\u201d and culminates with a tapestry showing a unicorn caught in an octagonal pen. For ten points, identify this practice of killing animals.", "answer": "<b> hunt</b>ing", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "One man with this name was murdered by a mob led by Scipio Nasica, while another was killed by Lucius Opimius and his allies. One man with this name had his policies rolled back while he oversaw the resettlement of Carthage as part of his Sempronian Laws. Two men with this cognomen served as plebeian tribunes and tried to break up the lands of wealthy landowners. For ten points, name this cognomen of Tiberius and Gaius, two brothers who were killed for proposing reforms of the Roman Republic.", "answer": "<b> Gracchus</b> (accept Tiberius and/or Gaius<b> Gracchus</b>; accept descriptions of the<b> Gracchi </b>brothers; accept<b> Tiberius</b> until \u201cLucius\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This man labeled rival Rick Stokes an \u201cUncle Tom\u201d during a campaign against the Alice Democratic club. He noted that \u201cwe are coming out to fight the lies, the myths, the distortions\u201d in his Hope Speech, given in opposition to a bill mandating discriminatory requirements to work in public schools. This man\u2019s murderer claimed to have gone insane after a Twinkie binge. Dan White assassinated, for ten points, what\u201cMayor of Castro Street,\u201d the first openly gay man to be elected to political office in California?", "answer": "Harvey<b> Milk</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One of these women saved her first husband\u2019s life by pleading with the leader of a band of outlaws. One of these people died childless after criticizing a man for his public dancing. Another of these women bore a child who died soon after birth, which was divine punishment for committing adultery with a man who had earlier watched her bathe; that woman\u2019s next child succeeded her husband as the king of Israel. For ten points, name this group of women, including Abigail, Michal, and Bathsheba, who were spouses of a certain Jewish monarch.", "answer": "<b> wives of David</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Welsh people settled this region\u2019s Chubut Valley, and it is home to a glacier that is still advancing, the Perito Moreno. The first president of one country that shares it is memorialized in its Bernardo O\u2019Higgins National Park. Its native Tehuelche [tuh-wel-chee] people were taller than Europeans at first contact, leading to the legend that it was inhabited by giants. For ten points, name this region, sometimes defined as including the archipelago of Tierra del Fuego, that takes up the southern portion of Chile and Argentina.", "answer": "<b> Patagonia</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "Among the oldest recorded examples of these objects are the Lakshmi Plaques of the Chera dynasty and the Maneless Lions created by King Mahasen. In Jaffna, the \u201cDutch Dumps\u201d were examples of these items made out of copper by the Dutch East India Company. These items were punch-marked in early Indian history. Akbar commemorated a new millennium of Islamic history by inscribing \u201calf\u201d on these objects. In the 20th century, the value of these objects changed via decimalization, so 100 Indian paisa are equivalent to 1 rupee. For ten points, name these objects studied by numismatists interested in early Indian economies.", "answer": "<b> coin</b>s (prompt on other terms, like money, currency, etc.; do not accept or prompt on descriptions of paper money) Page 2", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "An attempt to cut this country in half was stopped at the Battle of Raate Road. A neighboring country created the puppet Terijoki [\u201dterry\u201d-yoh-kee] Government for this nation. Enemy units encircled by this country\u2019s military were known as<em> motti</em>. This nation\u2019s ski troops helped to hold a defensive line named for Field Marshal Mannerheim. An anti-tank weapon called the Molotov cocktail originated in, for ten points, what Scandinavian country that lost the Winter War to its neighbor, the Soviet Union?", "answer": "<b> Finland</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "During this event, the Battle of Groix foiled an attempted landing at Quiberon Bay. During a part of this event, the \u201cinfernal columns\u201d of Louis Tourreau tied humans into rafts to drown in the Loire. One uprising against this event occurred on the 13 of Vend\u00b4emaire and was crushed with a \u201cwhiff of grapeshot\u201dby the man who won the Siege of Toulon during this event. The Vend\u00b4ee and armies of \u00b4emigr\u00b4es fought against, for ten points, what event, opposed by royalists loyal to Louis XVI?", "answer": "<b> French Revolution</b> of 1789", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man, who refused payment from the Santa Fe Railroad Company, succeeded William Bankhead in his highest post. This politician commonly wore cowboy boots in his district and held meetings among a group of friends that he called the Board of Education. This prot\u00b4eg\u00b4e of John Nance Garner mentored Lyndon Johnson in the Senate. For ten points, name this Democrat from Texas, the longest-serving Speaker of the US House of Representatives.", "answer": "Samuel Taliaferro<b> Rayburn</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One cause of this event was the switch from narrow, riverside farm lots to square lots; that switch was enforced by surveyors on the orders of William McDougal. The leaders of this event ordered the execution of Thomas Scott. This rebellion\u2019s leader returned to lead the ill-fated North West Rebellion several years later. The province of Manitoba was established as part of the resolution to, for ten points, what 1869 Metis uprising led by Louis Riel, named for a colony that was itself named after a waterway?", "answer": "<b> Red River</b> Rebellion (or Uprising, etc.; prompt on Louis Riel\u2019s (First) Rebellion before \u201cRiel\u201dis read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man was acquitted by Jonathan Sewall in a case in which his crewmen physically resisted the attempts of an inspector to search the<em> Lydia</em>. This man, who allegedly used claims of gout to avoid dealing with political issues, left his successor, James Bowdoin, to deal with Shays\u2019 Rebellion after leaving office as the first Governor of Massachusetts. This man, but none of his colleagues, had his name printed at the bottom of the Dunlap Broadside. For ten points, name this Founding Father known for his large signature on the Declaration of Independence.", "answer": "John<b> Hancock</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In a play by this author, the stoic Harry Heegan is disabled while fighting in World War I. This author wrote a play in which Minnie Powell takes the fall for two independence fighters by taking a bag of bombs from their room. This author of<em> The Silver Tassie</em> wrote a play in which an unexpected inheritance causes Captain Jack to purchase a new suit, but he later laments that the world is in a state of chaos when his son is killed by the IRA. For ten points, name this author of<em> The Shadow of a Gunman</em> and<em> Juno and the</em> <em>Paycock</em>.", "answer": "Sean<b> O\u2019Casey</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Drama"}, {}, {"question": "Dixon Lewis helped this president create an institution to manage the money supply. The Independent Treasury Act was passed under this president, who vetoed a bill that would have raised $500,000 for the improvement of rivers and harbors. Abraham Lincoln asked this president to point out the exact spot where American blood was shed in opposing a war fought during his presidency. Whigs chanted \u201cWho is [this man]?\u201d during a race when he was chosen as a \u201cdark horse\u201d candidate by the Democratic party. For ten points, name this president who led the U.S. to victory in the Mexican-American War.", "answer": "James Knox<b> Polk</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One man with this surname lost an election after suspending the trial of J.R. Campbell for inciting mutiny in the newspaper Workers Weekly, and his re-election campaign was hurt by a forged letter from Grigori Zinoviev encouraging Communist rebellion. Another</b> <b>man with this surname faced a rebellion led by (+)</b> <b>Louis Riel in the Red River Colony</b> <b>and lost power after his administration was accused of accepting bribes for the contract of a (*)</b> trans-Canadian railroad. For ten points, give this surname of British Prime Minister, Ramsay, and the First Canadian Prime Minister, John.", "answer": "<b> MacDonald</b> (accept Ramsey<b> MacDonald</b> and/or John<b> MacDonald</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man rose to prominence after serving under Sancho the Strong at Graus. In this</b> <b>man\u2019s last battle, his dead body was propped up on a horse by his wife (+)</b> <b>Jimena. At</b> <b>Cabra, this owner of the sword Tizona was victorious against Garcia Ordonez, though because he launched an unauthorized expedition into (*)</b> Granada, he was exiled by Alfonso VI and began fighting for Zaragoza. For ten points, name this Castilian commander whose name means \u201cthe lord,\u201d a national hero of the Reconquista era.", "answer": "<b> El Cid</b> (or Rodrigo<b> Diaz</b> de Vivar; accept<b> Rodrigo</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s friendship with Yuval Ne\u2019eman allowed the US to discover that Israel had achieved nuclear capabilities. This man, who worked with Hermann Jahn on understanding the distortion of octahedral complexes, was the only scientist to testify against Julius (+) Oppenheimer during his security clearing. In his later years, this man supported the use of nuclear bombs to create an artificial harbor in Cape Thompson, Alaska, during Project Chariot. This man co-names, with Stanislaw (*)</b> Ulam, the design for a thermonuclear bomb. For ten points, name this Hungarian-American physicist, known as the \u201cfather of the hydrogen bomb.\u201d", "answer": "Edward<b> Teller</b> Page 10", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "<b>These events took place in the home of Harold and Martha Smith and were arranged by Swifty Lazar, an agent. Peter Morgan wrote a play based on these events, of which twelve</b> <b>occurred over the course of four weeks, producing 28 hours of (+)</b> <b>footage. One of these</b> <b>events opened with the question \u201cWhy didn\u2019t you burn the tapes?\u201d; at another point, one participant noted \u201cWell, when the (*)</b> President does it, that means that it is not illegal.\u201d For ten points, name these 1977 events in which a former president was questioned by David Frost on topics like the Watergate scandal.", "answer": "the Frost-<b>Nixon Interviews</b> (accept answers involving Richard<b> Nixon</b> being<b> interview</b>ed by David Frost)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This action\u2019s legitimacy is inferred from Article 27 Section 3 of a certain document. In 1986, this action prevented Nicaragua from being compensated after its victory in the International Court of Justice. Vyacheslav Molotov was noted for performing this action repeatedly, but the (+) Soviet Union was unable to perform this action during the Korean War. The possibility of this action leads to the use of straw polls prior to the official election of a new (*) </b> Secretary General. For ten points, name this action that can be performed by France, Russia, China, the UK, or the US, the five permanent members of a body of 15 countries within the United Nations.", "answer": "United Nations<b> Security Council veto</b> (accept descriptive answers that include both underlined parts, including<b> UNSC veto</b>; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Paul Painlev\u00b4e [pahn-lev-ay] supposedly compared Jean Racine to this man because both men\u2019s works \u201cdo not show the most probable distribution.\u201d Henri Poincare showed that</b> <b>Alphonse Bertillon\u2019s statements about this man were based on (+)</b> <b>misunderstandings of</b> <b>probability. Georges Picquart showed that this man could not have written the \u201cbordereau\u201ddiscovered in Maximilian von (*)</b> Schwartzkoppen\u2019s wastebasket. A court-martial at Rennes finally exonerated, for ten points, what French officer who spent four years in prison for supposedly passing military secrets to Germany?", "answer": "Alfred<b> Dreyfus</b> Page 11", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>From 2011 to 2016, this country\u2019s president was a musician known as \u201cSweet Mickey.\u201dJocelerme Privert is serving is the interim President of this country after the resignation of Michel Martelly. In August 2016, the UN acknowledged that (+) Nepalese workers were the origin of a devastating cholera outbreak in this country. The majority of casualties of 2016\u2019s Hurricane (*) </b> Matthew were from this country. For ten points, name this country where hundreds of thousands of people died after a 2010 earthquake that devastating its capital, Port-au-Prince.", "answer": "<b> Haiti</b>  (1) <b>This colony grew out of the prior established Oil River Protectorate. Frederick</b> <b>Lugard consolidated this colony from Southern and Northern holdings, the latter of</b> <b>which was centered at (+)</b> <b>Zungeru. Nnamdi Azikiwe became this country\u2019s first</b> <b>Zungeru. Nnamdi Azikiwe became this country\u2019s first</b> <b>post-independence president, but its arbitrarily drawn (*)</b> <b>post-independence president, but its arbitrarily drawn (*)</b> British-era borders still lead to tensions between the Igbo and Yoruba tribes. For ten points, name this country, formerly the site of a colony centered at Lagos. ANSWER: British<b> Nigeria</b> (accept Federal Republic of<b> Nigeria</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}